[Music]
Reedman reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Rita chapter
4 Jonas rode at a leisurely pace, glancing at the bike ports beside the
buildings to see if he could spot ashers He didn't often do his volunteer
hours with his friend because Asher frequently fooled around and made
serious work a little difficult. But now, with 12 coming so soon and the volunteer
hours ending didn't seem to matter. The freedom to choose where to spend those
hours had always seemed a wonderful luxury to Jonas; other hours of the day were so carefully
regulated. He remembered when he had become an Eight, as Lily would do shortly,
and had been faced with that freedom of choice. The eths always set out on their
first volunteer hour a little nervously, giggling and staying in groups of
friends. They almost invariably did their hours on Recreation Duty first, helping
with the younger ones in a place where they all still felt
comfortable. But with guidance, as they developed self-confidence and maturity,
they moved on to other jobs, gravitating toward those that would suit their own
interests and skills. A male 11 named Benjamin had done his entire nearly four
years in the Rehabilitation Center, working with citizens who had been
injured. It was rumored that he was a skilled bu now as the Rehabilitation
Directors themselves that he had even developed some machines and methods to hasten
rehabilitation. There was no doubt that Benjamin would receive his Assignment to
that field and would probably be permitted to bypass most of the
training. Jonas was impressed by the things Benjamin had achieved. He knew
them of course, since they had always been groupmates, but they never talked about
the boy's accomplishments because such a conversation would have been awkward for Benjamin.
There was never any comfortable way to mention or discuss one's successes
without breaking the rule against bragging, even if one didn't mean to. It
was a minor rule, rather like rudess punishable only by gentle
chastisement. But still. Better to steer clear of an occasion governed by a rule
which would be so easy to break. The area of dwellings behind him, Jonas rode past the community
structures, hoping to spot Asher's bicycle parked beside one of the small factories or office
buildings. He passed the child care Center where Lily stayed after school,
and a play area surrounding it. He rode through the Central Plaza and the large
Auditorium where public meetings were held. Jonas slowed and looked at the name
tags on the bicycles lined up outside the Nurturing Center. Then he checked those outside
Food Distribution; it was always fun to help with the deliveries, and he hoped he
would find his friend there there so that they could go together on the daily
rounds, carrying the cartons of supplies into the dwellings of the
community. But he finally found Asher's bicycle— —leaning, as usual, instead of
upright in its port, as it should have been— —at the House of the Old. There was
only one other child's bicycle there, that of a female 11 named
Fiona. Jonas liked Fiona. She was a good student, quiet and
polite, but she had a sense of fun as well, and it didn't surprise him that she
was working with Asher today. He parked his bicycle neatly in
the port beside theirs and entered the building. "Hello, Jonas," the attendant at
the front desk said. She handed in the signup sheet and stamped her own official seal beside his
signature. All of his volunteer hours would be carefully tabulated at the Hall of Open
Records. Once, long ago, it was whispered among the children that 11 had arrived
at the Ceremony of 12 only to hear a public announcement but he had not
completed the required number of volunteer hours and would not, therefore,
be given his Assignment. He had been permitted an additional month in which
to complete the hours, and then given his Assignment privately, with no applause, no
celebration: a disgrace that had clouded his entire future. "It's good to have some
volunteers here today," the attendant told him. "We celebrated a release this morning,
and that always throws the schedule off a little, so things get backed up." She
looked at a printed sheet. "Let's see.
Asher and Fiona are helping in the bathing room. Why don't you go join them
there? You know where it is, don't you?"
Jonas nodded, thanked her, and walked down the long hallway. He glanced into the
rooms on either side. The Old were sitting quietly, some visiting and
talking with one another, others doing hand workk and simple crafts. A few were
asleep each room was comfortably F Each room was comfortably furnished, the
floors covered with thick carpeting.
It was a serene and slow paced place, unlike the busy centers of manufactur
and distribution where the daily work of the community occurred. Jonas was glad
that he had, over the years, chosen to do his hours in a variety of places so that
he could experience the differences. He realized that not focusing on one area
meant he was left with not the slightest idea— —not even a guess —of what his Assignment would
be. He laughed softly. Thinking about the Ceremony again,
Jonas? he teased himself. But he suspected that with a date so near, probably all of
his friends were, too. He passed the Caretaker walking slowly with one of the Old in the hall.
"Hello, Jonas," the young uniformed man said, smiling pleasantly woman beside him, whose arm he
held, was hunched over as she shuffled along in her soft slippers. She looked toward Jonas and
smiled, but her dark eyes were clouded and blank. He realized she was blind. He
entered the bathing room with with its warm moist air and scent of cleansing
lotions. He removed his tunic, hung it carefully on a wall hook put on the
volunteer smok that was folded on a shelf. "Hi, Jonas!" Asher called from the
corner where he was kneeling beside a tub. Jonas saw Fiona nearby, at a
different tub. She looked up and smiled at him she was busy, gently washing a man
who lay in the warm water.
Jonas greeted them in the caretaking attendance at work nearby. Then he went
to the row of padded lounging chairs where others of the Old were waiting. He
had worked here before; he knew what to do. "Your turn Lissa he said, reading the
name tag on the woman's robe. "I'll just start the water and then help you up." He
pressed the button on a nearby empty tub and watched as the warm water flowed in
through the many small openings on the sides. The tub would be filled in a
minute and the water flow would stop automatically. He helped the woman from
the chair, led her to the tub, removed her robe, and studied her with his hand on
her arm as she stepped in and lowered herself. She leaned back and sighed with
pleasure, her head on a soft cushioned headrest. "Comfortable?" he asked, and she
nodded, her eyes closed Jonah squeezed cleansing lotion onto the clean sponge
at the end of the tub and began to wash her frail
body. Last night he had watched as his father bathe the new child This was much
the same: the fragile skin, the soothing water, the gentle motion of his hand, slippery with
soap. The relaxed, peaceful smile on the woman's face reminded him of Gabriel
being bathed. And the nakedness, too. It was against the rules for children or
adults to look at another's nakedness; but the rule did not apply to new children or the
Old. Jonas was glad. It was a nuisance to keep oneself covered while changing for
games, and the required apology of one had by mistake glimpsed another's body was always
awkward. He couldn't see why it was necessary. He liked the feeling of safety
here in this warm and quiet room; he liked the expression of trust on the
woman's face as she lay in the water unprotected, exposed, and
free. From the corner of his eye he could his friend Fiona helped the old man from
the tub and tenderly pat his thin, naked body dry with an absorbent
cloth. She helped him into his robe. Jonas thought Lissa had drifted
into sleep, as the Old often did, and he was careful to keep his motions steady
and gentle so he wouldn't wake her. He was surprised when she spoke, her eyes still
closed. "This morning we celebrated the release of Roberto,"
she told him. "It was wonderful." "I knew Roberto Jonah said. "I helped with his
feeding the last time I was here, just a few weeks ago he's a very interesting
man Lissa opened her eyes happily. "They told his whole life before
they released him," she said. "They always do. But to be honest," she whispered with a
mischievous look, "some of the tellings are a little boring. I've even seen some
of the Old fall asleep during tellings— —when they released Edna recently. Did you
know Edna Jonah shook his head. He couldn't recall anyone named
Edna. "Well, they tried to make her life sound meaningful. And of course," she added
primly, "all lives are meaningful, I don't mean that they
aren't. But Edna. My goodness. She was a birth mother and then she worked in Food
Production for years, until she came here.
She never even had a family un it Lissa lifted her head and looked
around to make sure no one else was listening. Then she confided, "I don't think Edna was very
smart." Jonas laughed. He rinsed her left arm, laid it back into the water began to
wash her feet. She murmured with pleasure as he massaged her feet with the sponge.
"But Roberto's life was wonderful Lorissa went on, after a moment. "He had been an
Instructor of Els you know how important that is— —and he'd been on the Planning
Committee. And— —goodness, I don't know how he found the time— —he also raised two
very successful children, and he was also the one who did the landscaping design
for the Central Plaza. He didn't do the actual labor, of course." "Now you're back.
Lean forward and I'll help you sit up."
Jonas put his arm around her and supported her as she sat. He squeezed the sponge against her
back and began to rub her sharp Bon shoulders. "Tell me about the
celebration." "Well, there was the telling of his life. That is always first. Then
the toast. We all raised our glasses and cheered. We chanted the anthem. He made a
lovely goodbye speech several of us made little speeches wishing him well. I
didn't, though. I've never been fond of public speaking. "He was thrilled. You should have
seen the look on his face when they let him go." Jonas slowed the strokes of his hand
on her back
thoughtfully Lissa he asked, "what happens when they make the
actual release? Where exactly did Roberto go?" She lifted her bare wet shoulders in
a small shrug. "I don't know. I don't think anybody does, except the
committee. He just bowed to all of us and then walked, like they all do, through the
special door in the Releasing Room. But you should have seen his look. Pure happiness, I'd call
it." Jonas grinned. "I wish I'd been there to see it Lissa
frown I don't know why they don't let children come. Not enough room, I guess.
They should enlarge the Releasing Room." "We'll have to suggest that to the
committee. Maybe they'd study it John said slightly and Lissa chortled with
laughter. Right! she hooted, and Jonas helped her from the top
[Music]